<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>4.0</title>
		
	<section>
		<title>Insulation Measures</title>
		
		Both wall and loft insulation measures have been modified so that:
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Thermal resistance values are now specified <emphasis>per millimeter</emphasis>;
					You must divide the resistances used in existing scenarios by the thicknesses to
					preserve the behaviour. This has the consequence that you can try different thicknesses
					and see the effect of change in resistance. 
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Thermal resistances can now be specified as a function of the house's condition rather
					than just as a constant value.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					If you really want, you can specify the resultant u-value of the surface after insulating,
					again as a function of the house's condition. This has a likelihood of causing incoherent
					scenarios unless the function is comprehensive, so use with caution.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		The suitability criteria for wall insulation measures are now user-definable,
		so if you want to you can apply cavity wall insulation to a sandstone wall or similar.
		
		If you relax the suitability criteria to allow reinsulation of an already insulated wall,
		the new insulation will apply additively on top of existing insulation, unless you have used
		the resultant u-value feature.
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Element Names</title>
		
		All naming attributes for elements have been changed to <code>name</code>name; all
		attributes previously called <code>id</code>, on actions, measures, groups, tariffs and so on
		are now called <code>name</code>.
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Tilted Loans</title>
		
		The repayment series for loans can be tilted geometrically using the new <code>tilt</code>
		attribute on <xref linkend="ref.finance.with-loan" />.
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>SAP Scores</title>
		
		An operating cost score defined in the same way as SAP score can be calculated using
		<xref linkend="ref.house.fuel-cost-index" />. This is not identical to a SAP score,
		unless used in the right way, so check the documentation for it before getting carried away.
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Batch</title>
		We've added batch running to the model. This introduces a new set of elements which are use outside of a scenario to control its inputs. 
		These may be found in <xref linkend="cat--Batch" />. 
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Table Data</title>
		
		<para>
		It is now possible to include tabular data in the NHM. 
		If you tag your scenario with the word 'table' in the user interface, then it will be treated as tab-separated tabular data in the editor window.
		 </para>
		 
		 <para>
		 We've added an extra kind of include to be used with tables.
		 If you use <code><![CDATA[<xi:include href="nhm:table/id/some_id"/>]]></code> then it will transform the scenario with that id into a <xref linkend="ref.table" /> before including it.  
		 </para>
		 
		 <para>
			Tables includes may contain a 'run' column which denotes which batch run the row provides data for. 
			This allows multiple rows to be specified in the input table per run. 
			If a 'run' column is included, Any other column which does not begin with a '$' symbol will be used to generate extra input variables from those which exist already.
		 </para>
	
		<example>
			<title>Table to XML Transformation</title>
			
			<table>
				<title>Original Table Input By User</title>
				
				<tgroup cols="3">
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>run</entry>
							<entry>date</entry>
							<entry>$a</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>1</entry>
							<entry>2013</entry>
							<entry>10</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>1</entry>
							<entry>2014</entry>
							<entry>20</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>2</entry>
							<entry>2013</entry>
							<entry>15</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>2</entry>
							<entry>2014</entry>
							<entry>30</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
	
			<table>
				<title>Automatically Widened Table (never actually seen by user)</title>
				<tgroup cols='2'>
					<thead>
						<row>
							<entry>$a-2013</entry>
							<entry>$a-2014</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry>10</entry>
							<entry>20</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry>15</entry>
							<entry>30</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
	
			Widened table in XML form which will be included in the batch XML:
			<programlisting language="xml">
				<![CDATA[
					<table>
						<header>
							<cell value="$a-2013" />
							<cell value="$a-2014" />
						</header>
						<row>
							<cell value="10" />
							<cell value="20" />
						</row>
						<row>
							<cell value="15" />
							<cell value="30" />
						</row>
					</table>
				]]>
			</programlisting>
		</example>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Reporting Changes</title>
		<para>We have added reporting modes to <xref linkend="ref.report.aggregate" />.
		These modes make it output less data when it would otherwise, and may also do some calculations over time.
		They are intended to be used in batch mode, since putting out large tables of data per scenario would be unhelpful in this case.
		Most other reports are disallowed when running in batch mode for the same reason.</para>
		
		<para>Most reports are now disabled by default. 
		We have added elements to turn each of them back on, which may be found in <xref linkend="cat--Reports" />.</para>
		
		<para>Aggregations <xref linkend="ref.aggregate.mean" />, <xref linkend="ref.aggregate.sum" /> and <xref linkend="ref.aggregate.count" /> now have a name attribute.
		This overrides their automatically generated column headers.
		This is useful because the generated headers are often quite long. 
		It's also sometimes necessary if you use batch running to vary an attribute in a report, since the auto-generated column name can trick the system into making extra columns.   
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Removed <code><![CDATA[<report.group-members>]]></code> and replaced it with <xref linkend="ref.report.dwellings" />.
			This new report observes the dwellings in a single group. It has user customizable fields.
			It also records whether a dwelling entered, left or remained in the group since the last time it was reported on.
			<xref linkend="ref.report.dwellings" /> also makes use of <xref linkend="cat--Reporting Modes" />.
			If it is used with <xref linkend="ref.mode.on-change" />, a change is defined as when a dwelling enters or exits the group, or the value of one of its fields changes.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			User-specified columns in reports now come out in the order in which they were written by the scenario author.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			<xref linkend="ref.report.aggregate" /> now outputs a table which is long rather than wide. It may produce multiple rows per date, and has an extra column for group. 
			If it is used together with <xref linkend="ref.division.by-combination" />, then there will be many group columns: one for each different function used to produce the combination.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>f.let and f.yield</title>
		
		These elements have been renamed to <code>function.let</code> and <code>function.yield</code> for clarity.
		<code><![CDATA[<f.let>]]></code> may now contain snapshot elements.
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Scenario Description</title>
		
		Added a description element to a scenario to allow separate descriptions to be assigned to a version of a scenario.
	</section>
</section>
