<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<title>4.3</title>
	
	<section>
		<title>Reset Actions</title>
		<para>
			To allow the imputation schema to be expressed explicitly in a scenario, we have added some actions which
			reset the thermal properties of walls, glazing, doors, floors and roofs. These actions use user-defined functions
			to compute the new thermal properties, but compute the function for each wall, door and do on in turn.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			To complement these, we have added some special functions which allow access to information about the <emphasis>current</emphasis>
			wall, door, and so on, which are only usable within the associated reset actions
		</para>
		
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<title>Reset Actions</title>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.action.reset-doors" />          </listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.action.reset-floors" />         </listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.action.reset-glazing" />        </listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.action.reset-roofs" />          </listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.action.reset-walls" /> </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<title>Special Functions</title>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.floor.sap-ground-floor-u-value" /> </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.floor.is-on-ground" />             </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.door.type" />                      </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.glazing.frame-type" />             </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.glazing.insulation-type" />        </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.glazing.type" />                   </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.wall.construction" />              </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.wall.infiltration" />              </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.wall.insulation-thickness" />      </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.wall.k-value" />                   </listitem>
			<listitem> <xref linkend="ref.wall.u-value" />                   </listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Random Number Functions</title>
		
		<para>
			Added random number functions which may be used in the scenario. These are intended for use with the new scaling actions to allow 'fuzzing' of the housing stock.
			That is, to introduce some randomness in an attempt to account for real life variation and measurement error.
		</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.random.gaussian" /></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.random.uniform" /></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.random.triangular" /></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Scaling Actions</title>
		
		<para>
			We have introduced a number of scaling actions. These increase or decrease some house value by a proportion. This proportion is specified as a number function, so it may vary on a per-house basis.
			These actions are intended to be used at the beginning of a scenario to correct systematic errors in the stock, or to explore 'what-if' scenarios.			
		</para>
		
		<para>
			To go with these actions, we have introduced some number functions which expose the value they change. 
			These are mainly intended for use in probes and reports to allow the results of the scaling actions to be seen, but may be used anywhere that a function would be used normally.
			An action to scale u-values was also considered, but has not been added since the same effect may be achieved for u-values using the impuation elements.
		</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.scale.efficiency" /> may affect one or more of the various space heating and hot water systems.</listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.heating-efficiency" /></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.scale.responsiveness" /> may affect either primary or secondary space heating or both.</listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.heating-responsiveness" /></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Lookup Tables</title>
			
		<para>
			We have added a function <xref linkend="ref.lookup" /> for expressing arbitrary n-dimensional 
			lookup tables, whose indices can be computed from arbitrary language elements.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Extra House Functions</title>
		
		<para>We have added the following house functions.</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.sap-age-band" /></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.roof-construction-type" /></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.floor-construction-type" /></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.floor-insulation-thickness" /></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.household-income"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.number-of-occupants"/></listitem>
			<listitem><xref linkend="ref.house.number-of-bedrooms"/></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Stock Report Now Optional</title>
		
		<para>
			Previously, we were including a JSON file containing the entire housing stock in the report zip produced for a scenario.
			This is now disabled by default, but may be turned on again by including the <xref linkend="ref.report.housing-stock" /> element in your scenario.			
		</para>
	</section>
</section>
