<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>5.1.0</title>

  <section>
    <title>Changes to quantisation</title>

    <para>
      The quantisation methods available have been extended to allow for fractional weights, and
      weights which vary between simulated houses. This change means that quantisation-related
      grossing errors can be eliminated.

      The default quantisation mode <emphasis>has been changed</emphasis>, so existing scenarios
      will behave slightly differently (they will no longer have any rounding errors in grossed
      figures).
    </para>

    <para>
      For more about the changes to quantisation, see the <xref linkend="ref.scenario" />
      element documentation, which details the new <code>weighting:</code> parameter available on
      all scenarios and how it is used when running a simulation.
    </para>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>New language elements</title>
    
    <para>
      These new elements have been added to the language, to assist in the validation of new
      stocks, and for general use.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Hot water tanks</title>
      <para>
        The two new elements <xref linkend="ref.house.has-hot-water-cylinder" /> and <xref
        linkend="ref.house.has-insulated-hot-water-cylinder" /> have been added which
        allow you to find out about the status of a hot water cylinder in a house.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Main heating system type</title>
      <para>
        The element <xref linkend="ref.house.main-heating-system-type" /> has been added,
        which allows you to report on the type of main heating system in a house.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Proportion of double glazed windows</title>

      <para>
        The element <xref linkend="ref.house.double-glazed-proportion" /> has been added,
        which will produce the proportion of a house's glazing which is double glazing.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
        <title>Measure to install insulation on a Hot Water Cylinder</title>
        <para>
            The element <xref linkend="ref.measure.hot-water-tank-insulation" /> has been added which will top-up insulation on an existing hot water cylinder.
        </para>
    </section>
    
     <section>
        <title>Measure to update an existing WarmAirHeatingSystem.</title>
        <para>
            The element <xref linkend="ref.measure.warm-air-system" /> has been added which will renew an existing Warm Air heating system.
        </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Access to per-house weights</title>

      <para>
        The element <xref linkend="ref.house.weight" /> has been added, which allows access to
        the weight of the current house. This should typically be used in preference to <xref
        linkend="ref.sim.quantum" />, when summing up weighted values.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
    	<title>Aggregate probes</title>
    	<para>
    		The <xref linkend="ref.probe.aggregate" /> element has been added, which allows users to
    		probe the aggregate effect of a measure (for example, to aggregate how many houses were suitable).
    	</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
    	<title>Improvement to <xref linkend="ref.action.set-heating-temperatures" /></title>
    	
    	<para>
	    	<xref linkend="ref.action.set-heating-temperatures" /> has a new argument
	    	<code>desired-heating-months:</code>, which is a convenience for selecting a 
	    	<code>threshold-external-temperature:</code> that results in a particular set of
	    	heating months under a house's current weather conditions (note that this does
			not exactly set the months in which the heating is on; it remains impossible to
			have the heating on in a month which is warmer than another month for which the heating
			is off).
    	</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
    	<title>Addition of <xref linkend="ref.house.mean-internal-temperature" /></title>
    	
    	<para>
    		This element has been added to aid in the production of statistical tables which
    		DECC publishes; it gives the mean internal temperature of the house over the whole year, 
    		as determined by SAP.
    	</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
  	<title>UI Improvements</title>
  	
  	<section>
  		<title>Report links</title>
  		
  		<para>
  			When viewing a report, the leftmost link at the top of the page now returns
  			to the front of the report, rather than to the scenario editor. To access the
  			scenario editor, follow the third link entitled "view scenario".
  		</para>
  	</section>
  	
  	<section>
  		<title>Quick preview graphs</title>
  		
  		<para>
  			Tabular outputs now have a small preview page available from their help section
  			(click the [+] link in the report index to view the help section). This allows a quick
  			view of the distribution and correlation of numerical outputs, broken down by
  			categorical outputs.
  		</para>
  	</section>
  	
  	<section>
  		<title>Improved behaviour of F4 key</title>
  		
  		<para>
  			Previously, the <code>F4</code> key could be used to navigate to includes.
  			Now it will also navigate to the definition of templates, or help for elements.
  		</para>
  	</section>
  </section>

	<section>
		<title>Performance Improvements</title>
		
		<para>
			The memory usage and CPU time associated with validation have been reduced, which should
			allow larger and more complex scenarios to be validated.
		</para>
	</section>

  <section>
    <title>Bugs fixed</title>
    <section>
      <title>Error in <xref linkend="ref.house.heat-loss" /></title>

      <para>
        <xref linkend="ref.house.heat-loss" /> was erroneously being negated and produced in
        kilowatts/degree, rather than being positive and in watts/degree. This has been fixed, and
        the documentation for the element has been improved.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
    	<title>Error in lookup</title>
    	
    	<para>
    		<xref linkend="ref.lookup" /> did not behave correctly when used in a time-sensitive context
    		(for example in defining carbon factors) if one of the row-keys was itself time sensitive; the change
    		in value due to the row key changing did not always happen. This has been fixed.
    	</para>
    </section>
  </section>

</section>
