<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>5.1.1</title>

  <section>
    <title>Language Changes</title>
    <section>
      <title>Sequencing of probe outputs</title>
      <para>
        Probe elements behaviour has been changed so that report columns are produced in the same
        order as the <code>capture:</code> argument lists them. Previously they were produced in
        alphabetical order. In a related change, the documentation for probes has been updated to
        point out that the <code>name:</code> argument for any probed value can be used to determine
        the column heading in the report.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvement of solar PV model</title>
      <para>
        The solar photovoltaic model now distinguishes between energy used within the dwelling and
        energy exported to the grid. Scenarios can set the maximum proportion of generation which
        can be used within the dwelling, and a new fuel type has been introduced to allow the price
        for exported electricity to differ from the price of consumed electricity.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvement of <xref linkend="ref.action.remove-fuel-charge" /></title>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="ref.action.remove-fuel-charge" /> can now be used to remove
        <emphasis>all</emphasis> additional charges included in a dwelling's tariff, without having
        to know which charges may have been added. This is useful in performing a calculation within
        an <xref linkend="ref.under" /> function in which you want to be sure that a certain set
        of tariffs are being used, such as when calculating a SAP score.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Addition of random number state to sequence report</title>
      <para>
        The sequence report now has an additional column which gives the random number generator's
        internal state after each event is processed. This is only useful for determining at what
        point the random behaviour in two different runs has diverged.
      </para>
    </section>

	<section>
	  <title>Improvements to include and ~module</title>
	  <para>
		To help with the creation of reusable modules, a new include elemnt has been
		added, <code>include-modules</code>, which <emphasis>only</emphasis> includes
		modules or other <code>include-modules</code> statements in the top level of the
		referenced scenario. In addition to this, it is now legal to define a module
		twice; only the first definition has any effect.
	  </para>
	  <para>
		The upshot of this is that if you have modules which depend on each other, you no
		longer need to make sure you only include each of these dependencies once.
	  </para>
      <para>
        In addition, local names within a module can now be written directly by prefacing
        them with a slash; for example, the following
      </para>
      <programlisting language="lisp"><![CDATA[(~module M
      (template T [] /my-identifier))]]></programlisting>
      <para>
        is equivalent to
      </para>
      <programlisting language="lisp"><![CDATA[(template M/T [] M/my-identifier)]]></programlisting>
      <para>
        This special handling also applies to names starting with <code>#/</code> or
        <code>!/</code>, in which cases the module name is inserted before the slash, but
        after the punctuation.
      </para>

	</section>

    <section>
      <title>In-scenario assertions added</title>
      <para>
        To make it easier to check scenarios are working as intended, the <xref
        linkend="ref.assert" /> element has been added to the language. This can be used
        within any of the scheduling elements (like <xref linkend="ref.on.dates"/>), to
        test that a given condition holds at a certain point in the scenario, either for
        every house in a particular set, or for the simulation as a whole. Assertions can be
        configured to produce a warning, or to stop the simulation from running if they
        fail.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>house.insolation element added</title>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="ref.house.insolation" /> is a new element which lets you
        determine the average amount of insolation on an inclined plane under current
        weather conditions for the house, in kWh/year.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>house.air-change-rate added</title>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="ref.house.air-change-rate" /> is a new element which lets you
        access the energy calculator's prediction of the air change rate within a house.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>house.volume added</title>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="ref.house.volume" /> is a new element which provides the volume
        of a house in cubic metres.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>house.heat-load added</title>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="ref.house.heat-load" /> is a new element which provides the
        mean heat load in a house.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Simpler referencing</title>
      <para>
        In previous versions of the NHM, references to previously defined variables,
        actions, tests and so on had to be preceded with a <code>#</code> symbol. It is
        now possible simply to use the name, without a <code>#</code> symbol, although the
        old syntax is still supported.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improved error messages</title>
      <para>
        The error messages associated with some common scenario mistakes have been
        improved, to better signal the nature of the error.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Bounds checking on values calculated at runtime</title>
      <para>
        Most values which are computed at runtime are now bounds-checked, and warnings
        will be generated if they are not sensible. Checked values include heating system
        efficiencies, sizes, capex, opex, and hot water tank sizes; for example, if a
        measure's pricing function produces a negative price, a warning will be generated
        and the price will be clamped to zero.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Profiling information</title>
      <para>
        The top-level scenario element now has an argument <code>profile-depth:</code>
        which can be used to profile the running of your scenarios; if it is set to a
        positive number, an additional report will be generated showing how long different
        parts of the scenario are taking to run.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Multiple-value set, with counterfactuals</title>
      <para>
        The <code>set</code> action can now set multiple values at once, and can impose a
        counterfactual condition for computing those values. This makes it a more
        efficient alternative to repeated use of the <code>under</code> function, for
        example in the case where disaggregated fuel use is required under some complex
        set of counterfactual assumptions:
      </para>
      <programlisting language="lisp"><![CDATA[(set
      [mains-gas electricity]
      [(house.energy-use by-fuel:mainsgas) (house.energy-use by-fuel:peakelectricity)]
      under:(my-assumptions-template))]]></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Bugs Fixed</title>

    <section>
      <title>Uninsulated lofts imported correctly</title>
      <para>
        An oversight in the stock import code which meant that only dwellings with some
        loft insulation were considered to have a loft has been corrected; the EHS
        variable <code>FLITYPES</code> in the <code>services</code> file is now used to
        determine the presence of a loft. This increases the number of dwellings suitable
        for loft insulation in most stocks.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Non-determinism eliminated</title>
      <para>
        A programming error which produced a very occasional non-determinism between runs
        has been eliminated, ensuring total repeatability of pseudorandom model behaviour.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Validation faults corrected</title>
      <para>
	    A fault in <code>set</code> which broke the validator when the first argument (the
	    variable to set) could not be resolved has been corrected.
      </para>
      <para>
        Various other validation errors have been made more informative.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Energy calculation ventilation effects corrected</title>

      <para>
        A fault in the energy calculator has been corrected. Previously, the SAP
        adjustment which increases household ventilation in low-ventilation buildings was
        applied <emphasis>before</emphasis> the SAP adjustment which takes account of
        local wind speed when calculating the air change rate for a house. This caused a
        small excess increase in air change rate for those houses in which the structural
        air change rate was below 1, but the effect of local exposure would have raised it
        above one. The adjustments are now applied in the correct order (exposure effects
        first, occupants' adjustment second).
      </para>
      <para>
        The effect of the correction is small; under SAP 2012 assumptions, for the EHS
        2012 stock, the mean energy use has decreased from 22772.73 kWh/year to 22753.2
        kWh/year. The maximum has been reduced from 323656 to 323616, and the minimum from
        3206 to 3162
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
