<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" id="efficiency" xreflabel="Efficiency">
  <title>Heating Efficiencies</title>
  <para>
    Heat sources (for both water and spacing heating) in SAP are
    described by their <emphasis>efficiency</emphasis>. This represents
    how effective they are at converting fuel into heat, and is a number
    between 0 and 1 (usually expressed as a percentage between 0% and
    100%).
  </para>
  <para>
    To find out how much fuel was used by a heat source, take the amount
    of heat it will generate (in units of energy kWH) and divide it by
    the efficiency. This will give you the fuel consumption (also in
    units of energy kWH). The fuel consumption is therefore always
    higher than the amount of heat produced, reflecting any losses
    (usually from incomplete combustion of the fuel or heat lost as
    vapour).
  </para>
  <section>
    <title>Electric Heaters</title>
    <para>
      Electric resistive heaters are a kind of heat source where heat is
      made by driving electric current through a wire. They are assumed
      to have no losses - their efficiency is always 100%. The losses
      for electricity happened during the generation step, and may be
      considered accounted for in the higher price for electricity
      compared to most other fuels.
    </para>
    <para>
      This category includes all electric heaters except for heat pumps.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Heat Pumps</title>
    <para>
      Heat pumps are a type of heater which do not primarily generate
      heat themselves (although the losses from their pumping system do
      contribute to heating), but instead relocate it from the
      environment. They do not have an efficiency, but instead have a
      number called <emphasis>Coefficient of Performance</emphasis>
      (COP). COP is analogous to efficiency in most ways, but is allowed
      to be greater than 100%.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Boilers</title>
    <para>
      Boilers in SAP do not have a single efficiency number, but instead
      have seasonal winter and summer efficiencies. The winter
      efficiency is always higher, reflecting the changing effectiveness
      of the boiler under constant vs intermittent use.
    </para>
    <para>
      In SAP, space heating by a boiler uses the winter efficiency
      (heating is not generally required in summer).
    </para>
    <para>
      Water heating by a boiler uses a harmonic mean of the winter and
      summer efficiencies, weighted by the heat demands for space and
      water heating respectively.
    </para>
    <para>
      The summer efficiency of boilers is, by default, 1% lower than the
      winter efficiency. This number is based on a linear regression
      against the boiler
      <ulink url="http://www.ncm-pcdb.org.uk/sap/">Product
      Characeristics Database (PCDB)</ulink>, which showed that almost
      all boilers follow this pattern.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Other Corrections</title>
    <para>
      In addition to the above, SAP specifies a large number of
      situational adjustments to efficiency. If you want to know more
      about these, it is best to read the
      <ulink url="http://www.bre.co.uk/filelibrary/SAP/2009/SAP-2009_9-90.pdf">SAP
      2009 specification</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>
</section>
