<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>SAP/BREDEM 2012 Update Specification</title>
  <para>
    These are the changes which were needed to refit the NHM energy
    calculator into a more correct SAP 2012 / BREDEM 2012 implementation
    (given the limitations of the survey data).
  </para>
  <para>
    The relevant source documents are:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.bre.co.uk/filelibrary/SAP/2012/SAP-2012_9-92.pdf">SAP
        2012</ulink>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.bre.co.uk/filelibrary/bredem/BREDEM-2012-specification.pdf">BREDEM
        2012</ulink>
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <sect1>
    <title>Add Scenario Elements To Set Energy Calculator</title>
    <para>
      First set up your scenario as follows:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
(scenario
 ;; This will be the default value anyway, but is shown here for illustration.
 energy-calculator: BREDEM2012)
</programlisting>
    <para>
      Use a hypothetical action to evaluate some function with an
      alternative calculator for a house within the same scenario:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
(under
 (energy-calculator SAP2012)
 evaluate: (house.energy-use))
</programlisting>
    <para>
      The reason this is a hypothetical action, is so that you can't
      accidentally have some houses on one energy calculation and some
      on the other.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Glazing Bug</title>
    <para>
      There was a bug in the stock import where it was confusing
      percentages with proportions. This could occur if you set the
      double glazing proportion (percentagedoubleglazed in
      elevations.csv) to 99% or 1%.
    </para>
    <para>
      I've checked some stocks, and I don't believe this bug has ever
      actually been triggered.
    </para>
    <para>
      (This is why percentages should never be stored in actual data,
      and should be a presentation choice instead.)
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Carbon Factors</title>
    <para>
      Carbon factors default to 0.
    </para>
    <para>
      Counterfactual.carbon defaults to SAP 2012 values from Table 12.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Energy Cost Deflator</title>
    <para>
      Updated the energy cost deflator to use SAP 2012 numbers (Table
      12, worksheet step 256).
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Energy Content of Water</title>
    <para>
      Updated HotWaterConstants09.ENERGY<subscript>PERVOLUME</subscript>
      to SAP/BREDEM 2012 values.
    </para>
    <para>
      It's not clear why this has changed such a tiny amount from SAP
      2009 (from 4.19 to 4.18). The real value (from reality) is 4.184.
      Possibly they have changed their rounding strategy.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Heat Pump Split Rate</title>
    <para>
      SAP 2009 used whether or not the heat pump had an auxiliary for
      the split-rate (proportion of electricity which is
      on-peak/off-peak) when providing space heating. This has been
      removed from SAP 2012.
    </para>
    <para>
      I have removed it from the NHM.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Responsiveness Adjustments</title>
    <para>
      Responsiveness adjustments to background temperature are now only
      taken from the main space heating system. Previously the NHM was
      taking a weighted average over all space heating systems based on
      the proportion of heat demand that they met.
    </para>
    <para>
      SAP does have something like this weighted average mechanism, but
      only for <emphasis>main</emphasis> space heating systems, and we
      only ever have one of those in the NHM.
    </para>
    <para>
      The actual algorithm now is that whatever generates the most space
      heat determines the responsiveness adjustments. This should always
      be the main space heating system.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Pump and Fan Running Time</title>
    <para>
      Pumps and fans in the NHM previously only ran for the part of the
      year while the space heating was on (with the constants involved
      adjusted to compensate).
    </para>
    <para>
      This meant that, if your heating ran for less time because of the
      degree days calculation (see BREDEM section 8), then the pumps and
      fans would also use less energy.
    </para>
    <para>
      We've removed this ability, since neither SAP nor BREDEM mention
      it.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Cooking</title>
    <para>
      This is based on BREDEM 2012 1M, 1N and 1O. Cooker types are in
      BREDEM <emphasis>Table 5: Cooking type coefficients</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
      BREDEM 2012 1P and 1Q, relating to range cookers, are unused. We
      have no information about range cookers.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the stock import, dwellings are assigned a cooker as follows:
    </para>
    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If they use mains gas for either their space or water heating,
          then they will get an electric oven and gas hob (corresponds
          to &quot;Normal size cooker: electric / gas&quot;).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Otherwise, they will get an electric oven and electric hob
          (corresponds to &quot;Normal size cooker: electric&quot;).
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      There is no way to modify a dwelling's cooker in a scenario.
    </para>
    <para>
      In both energy calculator modes, we will calculate cooking energy
      using the BREDEM 2012 method (since SAP does not define a method
      for this).
    </para>
    <para>
      In SAP 2012 mode, the gains from cooking will be based on the
      cooking line in SAP <emphasis>Table 5: Internal Heat
      Gains</emphasis>. This means that in SAP 2012 mode, gains due to
      cooking <emphasis>will not depend</emphasis> on energy demand from
      cooking.
    </para>
    <para>
      Note that the <literal>house.fuel-cost-index</literal> element
      used to get the SAP score does't include cooking energy use in
      either energy calculator mode.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Solar Thermal Values from Stock</title>
    <para>
      Changed the defaults on measure.solar-dhw to be the same as the
      defaults in the stock.
    </para>
    <para>
      These come from the Cambridge Housing Model.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Primary Pipework Losses</title>
    <para>
      Primary pipework losses have changed since SAP 2009, and needed
      redoing from scratch.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is the same for both SAP 2012 and BREDEM 2012 calculators:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          SAP worksheet (59), Table 3 and Table H4
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          BREDEM 2.2.D, Tables 10, 11 and 12
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      Since we have no information about the <emphasis>water heating
      separately timed</emphasis> property in the hours per day primary
      hot lookup. We assume this is false (more pessimistic assumption).
    </para>
    <para>
      Implementation:
    </para>
    <orderedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Do not apply to combi-boilers, CPSUs, point-of-use hot water,
          immersion heaters, or solar water heaters.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Compute fraction pipework insulated (or use 1.0 for community
          heating)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Compute hours-per-day primary pipework hot based on month and
          heating controls (or use 3 for community heating).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Compute solar adjustment factor based on month and whether
          solar water heating is present.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Compute the loss.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Community Charging Adjustments</title>
    <para>
      Adjustements which only apply in SAP mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      If there is a community heating system, its energy consumption is
      modified based on charging type and heating controls according to
      SAP Table 4c.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the stock import, you can set this using
      <emphasis>communitychargingusagebased</emphasis> in
      <emphasis>space-heating.csv</emphasis>. On
      <emphasis>measure.district-heating</emphasis>, you can set this
      using <emphasis>charging-usage-based</emphasis>. In both cases, it
      defaults to false.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>def-adjustment</title>
    <para>
      <literal>def-adjustment</literal> is a scenario element which
      allows BEIS to implement arbitrary new energy-saving appliances.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is not part of either SAP or BREDEM specifications.
    </para>
    <para>
      Its effects have been disabled in SAP 2012 mode.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>context.calibration</title>
    <para>
      <literal>context.calibration</literal> is a scenario element which
      allows BEIS to recalibrate the energy calculator to evaluate an
      arbitrary function for each fuel.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is not part of either the SAP or BREDEM specifications.
    </para>
    <para>
      Its effects have been disabled in SAP 2012 mode.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Energy Calculator Constants</title>
    <para>
      <literal>context.energy-constants</literal> is a scenario element
      which allows BEIS to redefined constants inside the energy
      calculator.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is not part of either the SAP or BREDEM specifications.
    </para>
    <para>
      Its effects have been disabled in SAP 2012 mode.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Site Exposure</title>
    <para>
      This is the number from Table 21 in BREDEM 2012, which is applied
      as a multiplier to the air change rate due to fabric and
      deliberate ventilation in part 3E.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is locked to 1 (no effect) for the SAP 2012 calculator.
    </para>
    <para>
      The default exposure for a house will be
      <emphasis>average</emphasis> (multiplier of 1).
    </para>
    <para>
      We have not implemented a way to put this value in through the
      stock import.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can set it on a house in a scenario using
      <literal>action.set-site-exposure</literal>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Boiler Efficiency Adjustments</title>
    <para>
      This is in SAP 2012 Table 4c (3), and applies in both energy
      calculators.
    </para>
    <para>
      These adjustments apply only to <emphasis>gas</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>oil</emphasis> boilers (following BRE's advice). We have
      assumed this means all types of gas boilers (including LPG).
    </para>
    <para>
      There is a 5% efficiency reduction for boilers which are lacking
      either <emphasis>thermostatic control of room
      temperature</emphasis>, or <emphasis>boiler interlock</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Boiler interlock</emphasis> is defined as having
      thermostatic control of <emphasis role="strong">both</emphasis>
      the room temperature <emphasis role="strong">and</emphasis> the
      hot water cylinder (if one is present).
    </para>
    <para>
      This applies to space heating only for combi boilers and CPSUs.
    </para>
    <para>
      It applies to both space heating and water heating for other kinds
      of boiler.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Heat Pump Efficiency Adjustments</title>
    <para>
      In SAP 2009 these are in Table 4c (4). In SAP 2012 there is no
      mention of them.
    </para>
    <para>
      We have removed them from the NHM.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Interzone Specific Heat Transfer</title>
    <para>
      This is computed in BREDEM 2012 3J.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the NHM, it defaults to 0.
    </para>
    <para>
      It has no effect in the SAP 2012 calculator.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the BREDEM 2012, it moves the unheated Zone 2 temperature
      towards the Zone 1 demand temperature.
    </para>
    <para>
      You cannot set it in the stock import.
    </para>
    <para>
      In a scenario, you can set it on a dwelling using
      <literal>action.set-interzone-specific-heat-transfer</literal>.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Appliances Base Energy</title>
    <para>
      This is different between SAP and BREDEM, although the formula is
      otherwise the same.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Thermal Bridging Coefficient</title>
    <para>
      We are using the simplified thermal bridge calculation, because we
      do not have enough information about the house to justify using
      the more complicated &quot;add up all the elements in a
      table&quot; method (we would likely be missing many of the
      elements, and so might under-estimate).
    </para>
    <para>
      This is described in the SAP 2012 worksheet step (36), and in
      BREDEM 2012 at Step 3A.b.
    </para>
    <para>
      The area of the house is multiplied by a <emphasis>Thermal bridge
      factor</emphasis>. In SAP 2012 mode, this factor is always fixed
      to 0.15. In BREDEM 2012 mode, it defaults to 0.15.
    </para>
    <para>
      We have not included a way to change the <emphasis>thermal bridge
      factor</emphasis> for a dwelling in the stock. You can change it
      on a dwelling inside a scenario using ==.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Footnote vii</emphasis> in BREDEM 2012 describes how to
      set this effectively:
    </para>
    <blockquote>
      <para>
        The value of y reflects the level of attention paid to limiting
        thermal bridge losses. 0.15 would be suitable for most homes
        built before 2002, when little attention was paid to thermal
        bridging. For a dwelling complying with the 2002 building
        regulations for England and Wales, or a similar standard, use
        0.11. For a dwelling built after 2006 a suitable value would be
        0.08.
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>
      Note that there is a minor error with the specification of units
      in BREDEM 2012. The units for the <emphasis>thermal bridge
      factor</emphasis> (should be W/m<superscript>2K</superscript>) and
      the <emphasis>thermal bridging loss</emphasis> (should be W/K) are
      reversed.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Degree Days vs Heating Months</title>
    <para>
      BREDEM 2012 specifies (see 8F, 8G, 8H) a degree-days based
      mechanism for working out a value called <emphasis>fraction of
      month heating is enabled</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
      This is a somewhat misleading property name: it actually controls
      what proportion of <emphasis>gains</emphasis> is reduced by the
      <emphasis>gains utilisation factor</emphasis>, and what proportion
      is used as is.
    </para>
    <para>
      In SAP 2012 there is no corresponding property, so this fraction
      is always set to 1 in SAP 2012 mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      We control when the heating is actually on using the
      <emphasis>desired-heating-months</emphasis> property on
      <literal>action.set-heating-temperatures</literal>. This property
      defaults to the SAP heating months (January to May, and then
      October to December (inclusive)). In SAP 2012 mode, you cannot
      change the heating-months, and this property will be ignored.
    </para>
    <para>
      There is an open question with BRE about whether there is an error
      in the BREDEM 2012 specification here.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Reduced Internal Gain</title>
    <para>
      Reduced internal gains is from SAP 2012, in column B of Table 5.
      The table mentions that is applies to the DFEE, TDEE, DER and TER
      for new dwellings, and nothing else.
    </para>
    <para>
      They never have any effect when the energy calculator is in SAP
      2012 mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      While reduced internal gains are not defined in BREDEM 2012, we
      have implemented them in the energy calculator in BREDEM 2012 mode
      since its gains calculations are quite similar.
    </para>
    <para>
      All houses constructed in the stock do not have reduced internal
      gains. You can enable it on a house in a scenario using
      <literal>action.reduced-internal-gains</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
      It has the following effects:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Metabolic gains reduced from 60W per person to 50W per person
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Lighting gains multiplied by 0.4
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Appliance gains multiplied by 0.67
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Cooking gains due to base load scaled by 23 / 35, and gains
          per person scaled by 5 / 7
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      It has no effect on the energy consumption of any of these, only
      their gains output.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Responsiveness</title>
    <para>
      Removed <literal>scale.responsiveness</literal>, as it was a
      poorly designed action, and does not fit well with the new lookup
      table approach.
    </para>
    <para>
      Removed the <emphasis>of:</emphasis> property from
      <literal>house.heating-responsiveness</literal>, since only the
      responsiveness of the primary space heating system is always
      relevant.
    </para>
    <para>
      SAP 2012 defines responsiveness of heating systems in Tables 4a
      and 4d. BREDEM explicitly defers to SAP for responsiveness (see
      BREDEM 2012 Appendix B).
    </para>
    <para>
      Corrected the responsiveness values in the NHM to match that
      lookup for both energy calculator modes.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is possible to set the responsiveness on
      <literal>measure.storage-heating</literal>. This is to allow for
      the modelling of improved modern storage heating. In SAP 2012
      mode, this value is ignored.
    </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              System
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Fuel
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Responsiveness
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              None (assumed portable heaters)
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Electric
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              CPSU
            </entry>
            <entry>
              *
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Combi Boiler
            </entry>
            <entry>
              *
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.75
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Other Boiler
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Coal or Biomass
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.75 or 0.5
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Other Boiler
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Not Solid
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Table 4d
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Heat pump
            </entry>
            <entry>
              *
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Table 4d
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Warm Air heat pump
            </entry>
            <entry>
              *
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Community
            </entry>
            <entry>
              *
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Storage heaters
            </entry>
            <entry>
              *
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0 to 0.8 depending on type
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Warm Air
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Electric
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.75
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Warm Air
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Not Electric
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Room Heater
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Coal or Biomass
            </entry>
            <entry>
              0.75 or 0.5 (never relevant)
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Room Heater
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Not Solid
            </entry>
            <entry>
              1 (never relevant)
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Solar PV</title>
    <para>
      Solar PV is now specified as per Appendix M of SAP 2012, and step
      10A or BREDEM 2012 (these are identical). This is the formula
      <literal>0.8 * peak power * solar flux * overshading factor</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is assumed to be south facing with a 30 degree tilt and average
      overshading.
    </para>
    <para>
      We have removed <emphasis>roof-coverage</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>efficiency</emphasis> from
      <literal>measure.solar-photovoltaic</literal>, and replaced them
      with <emphasis>size</emphasis>, which is the peak power rating of
      the installation measured in kW.
    </para>
    <para>
      The NHM no longer knows how much roof area the solar panels need.
      There are therefore no longer any suitability criteria relating to
      roof area, and the scenario author should consider writing their
      sizing function in terms of the size of the roof.
    </para>
    <para>
      In SAP 2012 mode, the <emphasis>own-use-proportion</emphasis>,
      which determines how much electricity is used in the home and how
      much is exported, is locked to 0.5. In BREDEM 2012 mode the
      calculation will use the value specified in
      <literal>measure.solar-photovoltaic</literal>. In either mode, the
      dwelling will never use more electricity than it has demand for.
    </para>
    <para>
      Generated electricity which is used in the dwelling is now divided
      between peak and off-peak based on the split rate for generation
      from Table 12a.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Storage Combi Storage Losses</title>
    <para>
      In SAP 2012, <emphasis>4.2 Storage Loss</emphasis> states the
      following:
    </para>
    <blockquote>
      <para>
        For combi boilers the storage loss factor is zero if the
        efficiency is taken from Table 4b. The loss is to be included
        for a storage combination boiler if its efficiency is the
        manufacturer’s declared value or is obtained from the Product
        Characteristics Database, using the data in Tables 2, 2a and 2b
        (its insulation thickness and volume are also to be provided by
        the manufacturer or obtained from the database).
      </para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>
      Based on this, we have added a property
      <emphasis>EfficiencySource</emphasis> to boilers. This has the
      following values:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>ManufacturerDeclared</emphasis> (storage loss is
          computed)
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>SAPDefault</emphasis> (storage loss is 0)
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      When you install a boiler measure, the efficiency source is always
      set to <emphasis>ManufacturerDeclared</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the stock import, this value is set to TODO
    </para>
    <para>
      This applies in both energy calculator modes.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Thermal Mass</title>
    <para>
      SAP 2012 implements two thermal mass computations:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In worksheet (34), summing up the thermal mass over all the
          elements of the house.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In Table 1f, a simple lookup with low, medium and high values.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      On the advice of BRE, we have changed the NHM to use the Table 1f
      method, with the following table used to classify walls according
      to whether their thermal mass should be low, medium or high. We
      then select the level with the largest wall area.
    </para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Wall Type
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Internal/External Insulation
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Thermal Mass Level
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Stone/Solid
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Uninsulated
            </entry>
            <entry>
              High
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Stone/Solid
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Insulated
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Low
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Timber
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Any
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Low
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Other
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Any
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Medium
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec align="left" />
        <colspec align="left" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              BRE-Specified Wall Type
            </entry>
            <entry>
              NHM Wall Type
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Stone/Solid
            </entry>
            <entry>
              SolidBrick/GraniteOrWhinstone/Sandstone
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              TImber
            </entry>
            <entry>
              TimberFrame
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              Other
            </entry>
            <entry>
              Cob/Cavity/SystemBuild/MetalFrame
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
      Internal and Party walls are not included in this calculation. Not
      are roofs or floors.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>k-values</emphasis> (thermal mass for fabric elements)
      have been removed from the imputation schema.
    </para>
    <para>
      The scenario language element <literal>wall.k-value</literal> has
      been removed.
    </para>
    <para>
      <literal>action.reset-floors</literal>,
      <literal>action.reset-walls</literal> and
      <literal>action.reset-roofs</literal> have had their
      <emphasis>k-value</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>party-k-value</emphasis> properties removed.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Occupancy</title>
    <para>
      In SAP 2012 mode, the energy calculator will always use the SAP
      assumed occupancy (worksheet step (42)).
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Glazing</title>
    <para>
      In SAP 2012 mode, the frame factors, gains transmittance and light
      transmittance for glazed surfaces are now always looked up from
      the relevant SAP tables.
    </para>
    <para>
      In BREDEM 2012 mode, they may be set using the imputation schema,
      <literal>action.reset-glazing</literal> or
      <literal>measure.install-glazing</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
      None of these values has changed from SAP 2009.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Door Glazing</title>
      <para>
        In both SAP 2012 and BREDEM 2012, glazed doors are used for
        providing <emphasis>lighting</emphasis> and <emphasis>solar
        gains</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can control the number and type of doors in the stock import
        file <emphasis>elevations.csv</emphasis>. The size of each doors
        is decided by the imputation schema.
      </para>
      <para>
        Doors are double glazed is the proportion of double glazing in
        the dwelling is &gt; 0.5, and single glazed otherwise. (This
        method was chosen since a large number of dwellings have only 1
        door, in which case it is a good approximation.)
      </para>
      <para>
        Door glazing is air insulated (as with window glazing).
      </para>
      <para>
        <literal>measure.install-glazing</literal> does not affect
        glazed doors, only windows.
      </para>
      <para>
        SAP also has a concept of semi-glazed doors, which affect
        lighting but not solar gains. We do not have any information
        about these in the surveys, and so do not include them.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Infiltration</title>
    <para>
      Infiltration is largely the same in both BREDEM 2012 and SAP 2012
      (with the exception of windows and doors in BREDEM, see below).
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Intermittent Fans</title>
      <para>
        The number of intermittent fans is set in
        <emphasis>ventilation.csv</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        It cannot be set in a scenario.
      </para>
      <para>
        This field previously had no effect, but now adds the correct
        amount of infiltration to the dwelling.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Passive Vents</title>
      <para>
        The number of passive vents is set in
        <emphasis>ventilation.csv</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        It cannot be set in a scenario.
      </para>
      <para>
        This field previously had no effect, but now adds the correct
        amount of infiltration to the dwelling.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>BackBoiler Flues and Chimneys</title>
      <para>
        Found a bug where flues and chimneys on BackBoilers were being
        previously counted twice. This no longer happens.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Walls</title>
      <para>
        BREDEM 2012 has a larger wall infiltration table with more kinds
        of wall than SAP 2012.
      </para>
      <para>
        Additionally, SAP specifies that you should use the value which
        applies to the largest area of wall, while BREDEM uses an
        area-wieghting method to average the values.
      </para>
      <para>
        The NHM uses the SAP method.
      </para>
      <para>
        The NHM provides ways to set the infiltration for a particular
        segment of wall in the stock import (imputation schema) and
        using <literal>action.reset-walls</literal>. In SAP 2012 mode,
        these are overridden with the SAP values.
      </para>
      <para>
        (I missed this during the earlier specification phase, so you
        may want to give some extra thought to it.)
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Floors</title>
      <para>
        Floor infiltration is defined in both SAP 2012 and BREDEM 2012
        as:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            0.1 for sealed suspended floors
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            0.2 for unsealed suspended floors
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            0 for other kinds of floor (solid floor)
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        Previously in the NHM, it was possible to set infiltration for
        every floor in the building. This does not make sense in either
        SAP or BREDEM 2012.
      </para>
      <para>
        Floor infiltration now only applies to the ground floor, and the
        ability to set it on each floor been removed from
        <literal>action.reset-floors</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
        All properties with suspended floors older than or equal to SAP
        age band E are considered to be unsealed in the stock (as per
        RDSap Table S5).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Windows and Doors</title>
      <para>
        SAP 2012 calculates window and door infiltration in worksheet
        steps (14) and (15) based on the proportion of windows and doors
        which are draught stripped.
      </para>
      <para>
        BREDEM 2012 does this in step 3D, which refers to Table 19. This
        does the following:
      </para>
      <orderedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Divides windows and doors into categories based on whether
            or not they are draught proofed, and how well they fit.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Assigns an air change rate to each category.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Takes an area weighted mean over the categories.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        We do not have the information required to implement the BREDEM
        algorithm, so we use the SAP 2012 implementation for both energy
        calculator modes.
      </para>
      <para>
        The draught stripped proportion may be set in the stock using
        the field
        <emphasis>windowsanddoorsdraughtstrippedproportion</emphasis> in
        <emphasis>ventilation.csv</emphasis>.
      </para>
      <para>
        It may be set in a scenario using
        <literal>measure.install-draught-proofing</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
        (A previous version of this specification incorrectly stated
        that the current NHM implementation was the BREDEM
        implementation. This was not true.)
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Hot Water Demand</title>
    <para>
      The model implements the SAP hot water demand from the worksheet
      step (43) in SAP 2012 mode.
    </para>
    <para>
      It implements the BREDEM 2012 hot water demand 2.1A to 2.1F in
      BREDEM 2012 mode.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Showers</title>
      <para>
        In stock import, there is now a field
        <emphasis>showertype</emphasis> in
        <emphasis>water-heating.csv</emphasis>. This value is based (as
        per BRE recommendation) on whether or not there is a second
        water heating system present in the dwelling:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Second system present -&gt; electric shower
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Not present -&gt; mixer shower
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        There is no way to change the shower type of a dwelling within a
        scenario.
      </para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Showers in BREDEM 2012</title>
        <para>
          In BREDEM mode, if a mixer shower is present, it will increase
          the hot water demand. There are two types of mixer shower in
          BREDEM (combi and non-combi). Which type is used to determine
          hot water demand will depend on whether or not the dwelling
          has a combi boiler. See BREDEM Table 6.
        </para>
        <para>
          In BREDEM mode, if an electric shower is present, it will
          consume some electricity. This electricity demand will be
          recorded under the <emphasis>water heating</emphasis> service
          type (the other possibly suitable service type would be
          <emphasis>appliances</emphasis>, but water heating seems more
          appropriate). See BREDEM section 2.3.
        </para>
        <para>
          BREDEM doesn't tell us anything about the ratio of peak and
          off-peak electricity. We have used the default peak/off-peak
          split from SAP for this ratio.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Showers in SAP 2012</title>
        <para>
          In SAP 2012 mode, the shower only affects the solar hot water
          use adjustment factor. This, in turn, affects the utilisation
          factor for solar hot water. See SAP 2012 (H7a) and Table H3.
        </para>
        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec align="left" />
            <colspec align="left" />
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Shower
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  Adjustment
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Electric
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  1.29
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  Mixer
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  0.64
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  None
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  1.09
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>House Facing</title>
    <para>
      This is extra request EXS-193, which we decided would be a useful
      part of this update.
    </para>
    <para>
      In the stock import, <emphasis>elevations.csv</emphasis> now has
      an <emphasis>anglefromnorth</emphasis> field (specified in
      radians).
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Solar Flux Calculation</title>
    <para>
      The solar flux calculation has been updated to SAP 2012 equation
      (U3). This effects natural light, solar gains, solar water heating
      and solar PV.
    </para>
    <para>
      This is the same as BREDEM 2012 Steps 2.4.1B, C and D and Table
      15.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Demand Temperatures</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>SAP Mode</title>
      <para>
        See SAP 2012 Table 9.
      </para>
      <para>
        In SAP mode, the zone 1 demand temperature is always 21.
      </para>
      <para>
        The zone 2 demand temperature is calculated from the heat loss
        parameter with an <emphasis>interzone temperature
        difference</emphasis> of 3 and an <emphasis>zone 2 heating
        proportion</emphasis> of 1.0. Using these parameters, the BREDEM
        2012 temperature calculation is identical to the SAP 2012
        calculation.
      </para>
      <para>
        None of the options in
        <literal>action.set-heating-temperatures</literal> have any
        effect in SAP mode.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>BREDEM Mode</title>
      <para>
        In BREDEM mode, the zone 1 demand temperature may be overridden,
        e.g.
        <literal>action.set-heating-temperatures living-area-temperature: 21</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are two options for the zone 2 demand temperature in
        BREDEM mode:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If it has been set directly (e.g.
            <literal>action.set-heating-temperatures rest-of-dwelling-temperature: 18</literal>).
            In this case, the <emphasis>interzone temperature
            difference</emphasis> and the <emphasis>zone 2 heating
            proportion</emphasis> have no effect.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Otherwise, it will be computed using the formula from BREDEM
            2012 7A to 7E.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <sect3>
        <title>Zone 2 Heating Proportion</title>
        <para>
          This is part of the BREDEM 2012 mean internal temperature
          calculation. In particular it is used to compute the zone 2
          demand temperature, by mixing between the zone 2 temperature
          selected by control and the zone zone 2 unheated temperature.
          See equation 7E.
        </para>
        <para>
          It is not present in SAP, and has no effect in the SAP 2012
          calculator (it is treated as having a value of 1.0 in SAP).
        </para>
        <para>
          It is present on the dwelling as a property which can be set
          using
          <literal>action.set-heating-temperatures rest-of-dwelling-heated-proportion: 1.0</literal>.
          It cannot be set in the stock import, and defaults to 1.0
          (100% of zone 2heated) for new dwellings.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Heating Schedule</title>
    <para>
      In SAP 2012 mode, will always use the heating schedule from Table
      9.
    </para>
    <para>
      This includes using the heating control type (Table 4e
      <emphasis>Control</emphasis> column) to lookup the zone 2
      schedule.
    </para>
    <para>
      In BREDEM 2012 mode, zone 1 and zone 2 will always use the same
      schedule, which you can set using
      <literal>action.set-heating-schedule</literal>.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Zone 2 Heating Schedule</title>
      <para>
        In SAP 2012 mode, zone 2 has a separate heating schedule. This
        depends on the zone 2 control parameter, which is calculated
        from the type of heating controls present. See SAP 2012 Tables 9
        and 4e (<emphasis>Control</emphasis> column).
      </para>
      <para>
        In BREDEM 2012 mode, there is no way to set a zone 2 heating
        schedule. Both zones will have the same schedule.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Weather</title>
    <para>
      Updated default weather to match average UK weather from SAP 2012.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are 4 weather tables in SAP (these are the same as BREDEM
      Appendix A):
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Table U1: Mean external temperature</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Table U2: Wind speed</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Table U3: Solar Radiation</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis>Table U4 Representative Latitude and height above
          mean sea level</emphasis>
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      (Note that the height above sea level is never actually used in
      the SAP worksheet.)
    </para>
    <para>
      SAP 2012 specifies that you should use region-specific weather
      when calculating energy use, fuel costs and emissions, but average
      UK weather when calculating the <emphasis>Energy Cost
      Rating</emphasis> (SAP score) or the <emphasis>Environment Impact
      Rating</emphasis>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Since the energy calculator in the NHM doesn't know which of those
      you are trying to calculate, we've chosen the following
      compromise:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In SAP 2012 mode, we will always use the UK average weather,
          regardless of any other values the user has specified in the
          scenario.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          In BREDEM 2012 mode, we will use the user specified weather
          for the region the dwelling is in.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>U-Values</title>
    <para>
      In BREDEM 2012 mode, u-values are determined in the stock based on
      the imputation schema.
    </para>
    <para>
      They may be altered in a scenario using the various
      <literal>action.reset-thing</literal> actions, or by installing
      some insulation (which will convert the u-value into a resistance,
      add it to the resistance of the new insulation, and then convert
      the result back into a u-value).
    </para>
    <para>
      In SAP 2012 mode, u-values are always looked up from the SAP
      tables.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Wall Thickness</title>
      <para>
        Wall thickness in SAP 2012 is used to determine the u-value of
        the ground floor, and a minimum u-value for stone walls.
      </para>
      <para>
        Previously, the SAP scenario included an override to wall
        thickness based on Table S3. However, I have removed this as it
        would override the known extra thickness of the wall due to
        insulation installed.
      </para>
      <para>
        The imputation schema still contains the thickness values from
        Table S3, with a couple of amendments:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            SAP 2009 contained extra rows for insulated walls. We have
            kept these.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            MetalFrame thickness is taken from the CHM.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>SAP Window U-Values</title>
      <para>
        This is SAP 2012 Table 6e and RdSAP Table S14. Of these, we use
        Table 6e, because the model contains information about frame
        type and insulation.
      </para>
      <para>
        (These tables agree on the values for single and secondary
        glazing, but Table 6e has more rows for double and triple
        glazing.)
      </para>
      <para>
        We have no information about any of footnotes 1 (roof windows),
        2 (metal frame gap) or 3 (semi-glazed doors), so we ignore them.
      </para>
      <para>
        We always use the most pessimistic value for the
        <emphasis>glazing gap</emphasis> (6mm) and <emphasis>En
        value</emphasis>, as we have no information about these.
      </para>
      <para>
        We do apply the curtains adjustment from section 3.2.
      </para>
      <para>
        Windows installed via the stock all have <emphasis>air
        insulation</emphasis>, and are a mixture of single and
        double-glazed based <emphasis>percentagedoubleglazed</emphasis>
        in <emphasis>elevations.csv</emphasis>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>SAP Roof U-Values</title>
      <para>
        We use Table S9 (based on insulation thickness) for
        <emphasis>PitchedSlateOrTiles</emphasis> and
        <emphasis>Thatched</emphasis> roofs. We assume that the
        insulation thickness in the stock refers to joist insulation.
      </para>
      <para>
        We use Table S10 for <emphasis>Flat</emphasis> roofs, which
        looks up based on the age band.
      </para>
      <para>
        Party ceilings always have a u-value of 0.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>SAP Wall U-Values</title>
      <para>
        These are based on Tables S6, S7 and S8.
      </para>
      <para>
        We do not apply the extra resistance for dry-lining in S5.1.2,
        because we do not have any information about it.
      </para>
      <para>
        We do not have any knowledge about whether or not insulation
        recorded in the stock is <emphasis>as originally
        built</emphasis>. We therefore ignore the <emphasis>*</emphasis>
        footnote in Tables S6, S7 and S8.
      </para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Internal Walls</title>
        <para>
          Internal walls always have a u-value of 0.
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3>
        <title>Party Walls</title>
        <para>
          In SAP 2012, party walls are assigned u-values according to
          Table 3.6 and S8B. This simulated the movement of air within a
          cavity wall.
        </para>
        <para>
          In SAP 2012 mode, these u-values will be used. We have assumed
          that <emphasis>Metal Frame</emphasis> and
          <emphasis>Cob</emphasis> party walls count as not cavity for
          this purpose.
        </para>
        <para>
          In BREDEM mode, you may put a u-value on party walls using
          <literal>action.reset-walls</literal>. Party wall u-values
          default to 0 in the stock import.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>SAP Door U-Values</title>
      <para>
        This is based on Table S15A.
      </para>
      <para>
        We assume that all doors in the stock lead to the outside. We
        have no information about heated or unheated corridors or
        stairwells.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>SAP Floor U-Values</title>
      <para>
        All floors in a dwelling in the NHM are assumed to have the same
        floor insulation thickness. This, along with the construction
        type of the ground floor, are determined during the stock import
        based on the <emphasis>floors</emphasis> section of the
        imputation schema (original values from SAP 2012 Table S11).
      </para>
      <para>
        The insulation level for the floors may also be set in a
        scenario with <literal>measure.floor-insulation</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
        (In practice, only the ground floor and floors from overhanging
        storeys will have a heat-loss area, and we do not think there
        are many overhanging storeys in the stock.)
      </para>
      <para>
        (The construction type of floors other than the ground floor is
        not relevant, so we do not store it.)
      </para>
      <para>
        When calculating the u-value in SAP 2012 mode, we use:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            0 for party floors.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The formula from S5.5 if it is a ground floor.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Table S12 otherwise.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Deferred or Cancelled Items</title>
    <para>
      Things which we're not implementing as part of this project, but
      may warrant further thought.
    </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Space Cooling</title>
      <para>
        The NHM doesn't currently implement space cooling.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Electric CSPU Storage Loss</title>
      <para>
        The cylinder loss factor for an electric CPSU should always be
        0.022 kWh/litre/day.
      </para>
      <para>
        This is not implemented in the NHM.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Overshading</title>
      <para>
        We originally wanted to make overshading configurable in the
        scenario.
      </para>
      <para>
        We decided to abandon this when we realized that a dwelling has
        9 separate overshading properties: 1 for each point of an
        8-pointed compass, and 1 for solar PV / solar hot water.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Electricity Tariff Type</title>
      <para>
        Electricity tariffs are hardcoded to Economy 7 in the NHM.
      </para>
      <para>
        This affects electricity split rates, and also has a small
        effect on the responsiveness of storage heaters.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Ventilation Types</title>
      <para>
        See SAP worksheet step 24. Of the possible options, the NHM only
        implements <emphasis>natural ventilation</emphasis> (24d).
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Door Area</title>
      <para>
        Doors in SAP are 1.85 m<superscript>2</superscript> in area.
      </para>
      <para>
        I have not enforced in SAP 2012 mode, and I have also removed it
        from the sap-physics scenario.
      </para>
      <para>
        The reason for this is that some dwellings in the survey have
        too many doors (e.g. 50 doors on a tiny house). This is handled
        by a stock import step from the Cambridge Household Model stock
        import method, which shrinks all the doors if they take up too
        much area.
      </para>
      <para>
        For the future, I would suggest:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Remove the ability to set the size of doors from the
            imputation schema and from
            <literal>action.reset-doors</literal>, since it is an
            unhelpful level of detail.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Replace the door-shrinking step with some kind of
            door-throwing-away step.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Regions</title>
      <para>
        The NHM uses government office regions, because that is what the
        EHS provides.
      </para>
      <para>
        SAP weather tables U1 to U4 use some other region
        classification.
      </para>
      <para>
        We map these regions as follows (based on the Cambridge Houseing
        Model method):
      </para>
      <programlisting language="python">
  ehs_to_sap_region_mapping = {
      ## Taken from SpssHouseCaseReader.java#governmentOfficeRegionToSAPRegion
      &quot;NorthWest&quot;: &quot;WestPennines&quot;,
      &quot;NorthEast&quot;: &quot;Borders Scotland / Borders England&quot;,
      &quot;YorkshireAndTheHumber&quot;: &quot;North East England&quot;,
      &quot;WestMidlands&quot;: &quot;Midlands&quot;,
      &quot;EastEngland&quot;: &quot;East Anglia&quot;,
      &quot;EastMidlands&quot;: &quot;East Pennines&quot;,
      &quot;SouthWest&quot;: &quot;Severn Wales / Severn England&quot;,
      &quot;SouthEast&quot;: &quot;South East England&quot;,
      &quot;London&quot;: &quot;Thames&quot;,
      &quot;Wales&quot;: &quot;Wales&quot;,
      &quot;WesternScotland&quot;: &quot;West Scotland&quot;,
      &quot;EasternScotland&quot;: &quot;East Scotland&quot;,
      &quot;NorthernScotland&quot;: &quot;North East Scotland&quot;,
      &quot;NothernIreland&quot;: &quot;Nothern Ireland&quot;
  }
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Imputation Schema</title>
      <para>
        The imputation schema is a place for BEIS's evidence about the
        real values for various aspects of building physics.
      </para>
      <para>
        I believe it was originally populated from the intermediate
        unpublished BREDEM spec.
      </para>
      <para>
        We have not modified it as part of this work, because we do not
        know what changes BEIS have made to their copy and whether we
        would need to merge them in.
      </para>
      <para>
        This means there are a few things which might be worth
        considering here:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>
            k-values in the imputation schema no longer have any effect
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Age band L is not interpreted (these dwellings will use the
            values for band K).
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Some Scotland-specific values are missing
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The imputation schema's only effect in SAP 2012 mode is to
            determine wall thicknesses.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        If, in the future, BEIS commissions the work which will allow
        them to define their own energy calculators, it is likely that
        the imputation schema can be removed entirely.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Multiple Main Space Heating Systems</title>
      <para>
        The NHM only allows for a single main space heating system to be
        defined.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Room Heaters as Main Space Heating</title>
      <para>
        SAP allows for multiple room heaters to be treated as a single
        main space heating system.
      </para>
      <para>
        The NHM always treats room heaters as secondary space heating,
        and only allows one to be present in a dwelling.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Community Electricity Used For Heating Distribution</title>
      <para>
        In SAP 2012, 1% of the total energy demand of the community
        heating system added again as electricity demand. This is the
        electricity for pumping water around the system.
      </para>
      <para>
        This is not implemented in the NHM.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Appendix N Heat Pumps</title>
      <para>
        SAP 2012 Appendix N specifies a more complex model of heat
        pumps.
      </para>
      <para>
        The NHM does not implement this. The information to do so does
        not exist.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Environmental Impact Rating</title>
      <para>
        The NHM does not implement the SAP environmental impact rating
        calculation (SAP 2012 worksheet 274 and Section 14).
      </para>
      <para>
        It is easy to implement using the scenario language, or to
        calculate off-model.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>Missing Technologies</title>
      <para>
        The following technologies are not implemented in the NHM:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Micro CHP
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Community CHP
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Waste heat recovery
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Mechanical ventilation
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Micro hydro
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Wind turbines
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Heat pump warm air system
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Exhaust air heat pumps
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Underfloor heating (and alternatives to radiators in
            general)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            COMMENT PANDOC
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
